NYSUT Field Services Department Files. 6174/004
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Suffolk Regional Office: Correspondence, 1989 (Box 28, Folder 5)
  Legal complaint, Jeanette Clancy vs. Center Moriches Union Free School District Board of Education, with cover letter from Clancy to president of NYSUT, requesting refund of two years' dues, accusing union field representative of failure of duty of fair representation, March 10, with exhibit, teachers contract, September 1, 1987 August 31, 1991; related correspondence, May; memo to NYSUT counsel from field representative re nurse at Brookhaven hospital, charged by State Education Department for two errors in patient medication during one night shift at Southside, noting short staffing, November 15; regional reports, January 31 and October 27; document promoting value of public schools on Long Island; memo to local presidents from regional staff director inviting them to a strategy conference with school boards and administrators to counteract the "tax revolt" sentiment among citizen activist groups defeating school budget proposals, September 25; memo to NYSUT legal counsel inquiring whether there was any strong action the union could take against an anti-union (agency fee payer) teacher in the Middle Country school district (Centereach High School) who had been harassing the union for ten years, with attached letter from teacher to colleagues, July 7; letter from Jim Conti to field representative granting permission to negotiate a contract for a Jewish school as an independent activity, October 12, with earlier memo to file noting denial of permission because of conflict of interest; confidential memo to Jim Conti re negotiations with Suffolk County Community College and Brookhaven Hospital, June 2; memos re 3020a charges, filing problems, in Commack school district, May; letter from Jim Conti to insurance consultant Martin E. Segal Company requesting consultation with Nassau and Suffolk staff re self-insurance alternative to Empire Plan, February 13; confidential memo re letter to the editor of New York Teacher from teacher in Smithtown objecting to local's attendance incentive clause for distribution of Excellence In Teaching (EIT) funds, asserting that formula penalized teachers who became ill or had family emergencies, February 8; memo from Jim Conti re operational policy prohibiting attempts to organize locals already or recently represented by an AFL-CIO union, February 10; report by New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health, "Industrial Hygiene Investigation of Darkrooms, Ammerman Campus and Techni Center, Suffolk County Community College," December 19, 1988; letter from Central Islip Teachers Association, with chronology of filing of complaint to force district to comply with NYS Right to Know Law and federal OSHA Hazard Communication Standard, January 12
- Syracuse Regional Office: Correspondence, 1989 (Box 28, Folder 6)
  Memo from NYSUT legal counsel Bernard Ashe commenting on the proposed policy for the Liverpool Central School District, noting that this was the first he'd seen that appeared as if the writer had actually read the text of the federal Drug Free Workplace Act, November 13; letter outlining NYSUT's responsibilities for participation in CNYCOSH (Central New York Council on Safety & Health) conference on health and safety in the schools, December 21; related memo, November 2; memos from Jim Conti re interest by the North Syracuse Education Association about updating the Syracuse Teachers Association document, "Policy, Procedures and Information regarding Members Accused of Misconduct (Primarily Child Abuse) as a Result of Employment in the Syracuse City School District," December; copy of document; newsletter of the North Syracuse Education Association, Union Bug, n.d., c. December; memos re unsuccessful Briarcliff School-Related Personnel (SRP) organizing election, suggestion that NYSUT develop brochures targeted specifically to non-teaching staff, November 27; flyers and other materials; memo re newly organized East Syracuse-Minoa Teaching Assistants Association, December 4; newspaper clipping re approval by teachers of contract at Onondaga Community College, Syracuse Herald-Journal, November 1; letter to OCM BOCES from computer instructor whose request had been denied, defending his expertise, October 1; correspondence from NAACP, soliciting contributions for march on Washington, August 4, with cover memos forwarding it up the administration at NYSUT, August; letter to U.S. Department of Labor Occupational Safety & Health Administration from NYSUT Regional Staff Director, noting that the owner of the NYSUT office property, Widewaters Group, had addressed the problem of sewer-gas odor to NYSUT's satisfaction, June 12; earlier related correspondence with agency and Widewaters, April; materials re NYSUT fall regional conference of September 22-24; list of locals that had secured a new contract in the Syracuse region for 1989-1990; draft of letter from NYSUT to president of FNHP, Syracuse chapter (Cecelia Nabinger), noting non-payment of dues, outlining possible consequences, including disaffiliation and action to recover funds, June 2; finalized letter as sent to Nabinger, November 10; related memos between NYSUT officials re "problem local," May; reply from FNHP president Nabinger, December 1, denying anything improper, with attached lists of dues-paying members; memo to Jim Conti re possible strikes and critical impasses anticipated for September, with reply, June; plan documents, "The Chittenango Central School Effective Schools Process," April 5, and "Team Process Guide for Developing and Implementing Action Plans, Chittenango Central School," March 24, with cover memo to Chuck Santelli and Toni Cortese, April 24; draft letter to CSEA regional director re NEA victory in organizing 70 clerical personnel in the Liverpool school district, proposing arrangement between CSEA and NYSUT to satisfy no-raid clause in AFL-CIO constitution in order to defeat NEA in future representation elections, March 20, with reply from Jim Conti urging further conversation with CSEA before sending proposal, possibility for statewide arrangement, March 17; related correspondence and flyers re election, January; list of teachers' starting salaries in Syracuse area, 1988-89; proposed amendments to the Contractual Agreement between the Syracuse Teachers Association, Inc. and Syracuse City School District, January 1, 1988 through December 31 1991
- Utica Regional Office: Correspondence, 1989 (Box 28, Folder 7)
  Analysis by NYSUT legal counsel of Camden school district's new drug-free workplace policy, noting that it went far beyond what was required by new federal law, November 3, with cover letter from Jim Conti, November 7; text of policy as adopted by Camden Board of Education, with attached text of Drug-Free Workplace Act of 1988; memo from Jim Conti to NYSUT legal counsel re Elmira school district's new drug and alcohol abuse policy, asserting that it violated constitutional rights, Education Law, and human dignity, October 6; memo from the president of Herkimer County Community College to coach (?) re investigation of recruitment of out-of-state basketball players, use of New York State addresses for Indiana students to avoid paying out-of-state tuition and obtain financial aid, with handwritten note (by Jim Conti?) re situation, September 7; correspondence between Jim Conti and president of the New Hartford Teachers Association re cancer incidence at one school, June-July; correspondence re proposed state legislation that would tax the pensions of public employees, newsletter from member of Congress citing related Supreme Court ruling David v. Michigan Department of Treasury, May; newspaper clippings and correspondence re investigation of student cancer cluster at West Canada Valley school district, Herkimer County, relation to hazardous waste sites, March-April; memos re calculation (or not) of upper Mohawk Valley and central region BOCES salary medians for awarding of Excellence in Teaching funds, January-March
- United University Professions: Correspondence, 1989 (Box 28, Folder 8)
  Letter to research department of UUP, and attachments, re gender pay equity study being conducted for the newly affiliated, 100%-female Office Personnel Association of the Union-Endicott School District, other SRP units with similar gender predominance, basis for wage proposal, November 2; letter from UUP director to Jim Conti, asking for vote to give UUP a board seat on the National Committee on Pay Equity, October 12; list of upcoming staff meetings and events, with attached memos re potential attendance by Tom Hobart, September
- Organizing Correspondence, 1989 (Box 28, Folder 9)
  Memo to Jim Conti and other NYSUT officials re affiliations since 9/1/87, discussing difficulty of organizing larger units from a time resource perspective, need for organizing teams instead of regional office field staff, with attached list of locals, membership counts, and staff involvement, November 20, 1989; confidential notes of AFT advanced organizing seminar for community colleges, December 21; seminar program and related materials, including faculty questionnaire developed for California community college system and guide for designing an attitude survey; letter from NYSUT director of organizing re contacts at Hudson Valley Community College, October 30; memo to Jim Conti re dues rebate under union shop clauses, with attached memorandum from the Office of General Counsel of the National Labor Relations Board (NLRB), October 11; cover memo to organizers re attached text of district court's permanent injunction barring NLRB from implementing its health bargaining unit rule re American Hospital Association (AHA), August 7; related memo, May 25; mock- up of The Nurses Reporter, with cover memo to Jim Conti, May 17; memo to Conti re proposal by retired newspaper reporter and widower of a nurse with many contacts in the NYC municipal hospital system, referred by Westchester ALF-CIO Council, to start a pro-union newspaper for nurses, request for funding, May 9; list of colleges and universities with collective-bargaining agents in 1988, from the Chronicle of Higher Education, July 12; memo to Jim Conti re conversation with a member of the National Strength and Conditioning Association who wanted NYSUT to form a bargaining unit for strength and conditioning coaches, noting futility of the idea, July 6; letter from director of organizing re contact at Winthrop Hospital, June 28; clippings from Labor Relations Week; memo suggesting years' free dues as inducement for successful referral of new members, May 31; letter from NLRB declining review of charge of violation re Regents College Degrees and Examinations because it was determined that the entity was not an employer, May 26; article reporting advice of consultant to hospital administrators re keeping unions out (annual meeting of New England Health Care Assembly), with hand-written annotations and cover note to Jim Conti, April 24; article form Union Labor Report re study of 187 organizers from eight unions, concluding that low self esteem, low trust of others are characteristics of the most successful organizers; budget request for 1989-1990; newsletter of the National Center for the Study of Collective Bargaining in Higher Education and the Professions, published at Baruch College, re unionization among college faculty in 1989, January/February 1989; publication by labor lawyer, "The Supervisor's Handbook on Maintaining Non-Union Status," 1974; pro-union document by labor lawyer, "Government Intermedding Undercutting Union Autonomy: The Labor Lawyer's Challenge," n.d.; text of proposed Assembly bill providing higher reimbursement to hospitals for personnel costs, with cover memo from Jim Conti asking whether NYSUT should support it, March 7; letter from dean of the School of Public Health, New York State Department of Health, re first course in capital district on AIDS transmission for health care workers and emergency responders, February 7; article from Labor Relations Week noting fierce competition among three AFL-CIO unions to organize health care workers, with cover memo from Jim Conti re potential self-defeating consequences, February 17; memos requesting more information about the LaSalle School, for potential organizing efforts, with attached letter of inquiry from director of curriculum development re public school salaries, February; paper by Henry S. Farber, Department of Economics, MIT, "Trends in Worker Demand for Union Representation," December 1988; memo re proposed policy on organizing minimums for size of unit, December 7, 1988, with cover memo proposing meeting, February 9, 1989; press release re training on AIDS for health care workers and first responders, January 16, with seminar announcement; announcement for conference on union representatives in the health-care industry, March 6-7; memo re federal modification in the definition of "reasonable assurance" of continued employment for substitute teachers, need for state legislation to assure coverage of substitutes as public employees under the Taylor Law, impact on organizing potential, January 19; memo to organizers and regional staff directors instructing them to discard all copies of leaflet "Why Pay More for Less" because of an error, plans for reprinting a corrected version, January 12; memo re delivery of authorization cards and other materials to nurses at Columbia Presbyterian Hospital, January 26; letter to National Education Association (NEA) Board of Directors from NEA president Mary Hatwood Futrell recommending moratorium on raiding AFSME, SEIU, and IUOE locals, December 1987; letter to NYSUT president Tom Hobart from Federation of Nurses and Health Professionals asking for contracts to review language for a resource file, related memos, October
- Organizing Misc., 1989 (Box 28, Folder 10)
  Newsletters of the Division of Field Services, Organizing Bulletin
- Regional Staff Director Memos (1 of 2), 1988 (Box 28, Folder 11)
  January-June, 1988. Memo from Jim Conti to regional staff directors asking for participation in pay equity training session, June 14; Empire Plan Quarterly Experience Report, January March, 1988, produced for participating agencies in the New York State Health Insurance Plan by Division of Employee Benefits, New York State Department of Civil Service, with cover memo from Jim Conti, June 13; memo requesting teacher participation in facilitator training to assist locals in implementing shared decision making process, June 13; statewide listing of dues paid by locals, ranked by size of local and by amount of dues paid, May 13; listing of State Education Department's estimate of Excellence in Teaching funds for each of the state's 41 BOCES, May 13; memo re unofficial approval of safety and health grant request of $60,000 for 1988-89, plans for training, May 12; memo from NYSUT counsel James Sandner to NYSUT officers summarizing U.S. Supreme Court decision in Regents of the University of California v. Public Employment Relations Board, et al., re union use of employer internal mail system, May 12; explanation of IRS interpretation of Tax Reform Act of 1986, May 9; paper by PERB, "The Taylor Law: Procedures for Labor & Management," re recent PERB and Administrative Law Judge decisions and court cases, April 12; Tentative CSEA Agreement 1988-91; memo with attached satirical article on the limitations of management training, summary of U.S. Supreme Court decision on union use of employer internal mail system, May 2; teacher salary schedule average increases, 1986-87 and 1987-88, April 20; State Education Department memo re planning for grant applications for teacher mentor- internships and related materials, March-April; letter from director of state Department of Labor Division of Safety and Health, requesting identification of any hazardous work sites, March; memos re PERB mediation/arbitration program, with attached guidelines for pilot project, February; emergency extension of application deadline for Excellence in Teaching funds, from the State Education Department, January 6; New York Times clipping re labor situation in England, with cover memo that the U.K. might be setting the trend for the U.S., February 18; memo re rule for school districts that did not make timely application for EIT money, February 17; press release from State Education Department that Regents voted to require home-schooled students to take the same Pupil Evaluation Program (PEP) tests and Regents Preliminary Competency tests that students in school are required to take, extension of EIT application deadline, January 20; unemployment insurance decision re refusal of employment without just cause, appealed based on substantially lower salary offer, with cover memo, January 28; policies adopted by the Erie County BOCES and sold to BOCES districts around the state, and policy adopted by the Williamson Central School District; January 20; memo re AIDS operational policy, with attached NYSUT Position Paper on Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome (AIDS); chapter excerpt, "Unionism and Licensing of Public School Teachers: Impact on Wages and Educational Output," by Morris M. Kleiner and Daniel L. Petree, of book When Public Sector Workers Unionize, edited by Richard B. Freeman and Casey Ichniowski (University of Chicago Press), 1988; several issues of NEA-NY Advocate newsletter, April, June, and summer 1988, with cover note from Jim Conti to NYSUT officers and regional staff directors; newsletter of the Buffalo Teachers Federation, Provocator 6/88, volume 18, number 6; Commissioner's order staying the West Seneca school district from proceeding on determining a 3020a case without a hearing because the teacher filed just beyond the deadline to request such a hearing, June 14, 1988; CSEA/AFSME health insurance handbook supplement, describing alternatives to Empire Plan, April 19; article from Labor Studies Journal, "Union Membership Decline: Do the Goals of Unions Reflect the Changing Values of Workers?" by Jeanette A. Davy and Frank Shipper, Winter 1987-88; paper presented on April 12 and April 30, "The Taylor Law: Procedures Update for Labor & Management," re recent PERB and ALJ decisions and court cases; list of private schools educating children with handicapping conditions in New York, with cover letter, March 30; PERB administrative law judge decision in three cases against Rush-Henrietta Central School district, brought by Rush-Henrietta Employees' Association Buildings and Grounds, Bus Mechanics Chapter, Teachers Chapter, and Aides Chapter, over smoking ban, February 9; New York Times magazine clipping re end of seven-year AFL-CIO boycott of Coors beer; Bureau of National Affairs Daily Labor Report clippings; clippings re Empire Plan rate hikes; guidelines for eligibility for NYSUT Legal Defense Fund
- Regional Staff Director Memos (2 of 2), 1988 (Box 28, Folder 12)
  July-December, 1988. NYS Court of Appeals ruling affirming the judgment of the Appellate Division in CSEA v PERB and Luis Diaz, December 1; memo from Robert Diaz announcing that Excellence in Teaching (EIT) funds were available for distribution, December 14; NYSUT Executive Committee resolutions on public higher education in New York State, and on New York's fiscal crisis, December 2; survey of BOCES bargaining units to determine whether any employees are not represented by unit, December 8; materials re NYSUT support for creation of a NYS School Construction Authority, temporary exemption from Wicks Law, including legislative memorandum, New York Times clipping re political history of Wicks Law, list of state senators, December 7; state Supreme Court decision in Schneider v. Sobol, with cover memo re EIT funds, December 6; related memo, October 14; letter from NYS AFC-CIO re new Social Security rules that would make it more difficult for elderly and disabled claimants to file successful appeals after denial of benefits, with cover memo from Jim Conti and attached New York Times clipping, September-November; memo from Jim Conti re AFT education reform initiative, with list of prospective locals, November 11; letter from NYSUT president Tom Hobart to local presidents re anticipated changes in premiums to Empire Plan, with cover letter from Jim Conti, October 19; documents, cost-containment strategies available to participating agencies; letter from Tom Hobart re extension of Asbestos Hazard Emergency Response Act (AHERA), requiring asbestos management plans for public and private elementary and secondary schools, October 14; NYSUT Information Bulletin re NYS Mentor-Teacher Internship Program, revised August 1988; audit by the State Comptroller of the Empire Plan, with cover press release, September 28; memo re new Empire Plan benefit options, September 26; memo re annual salaries or stipends paid to NYSUT local presidents, school year 1987-88, September 12; median classroom teacher salaries, 1987-88; memo noting decrease in school district contribution to the New York State Teachers Retirement System, with attached NYSTRS administrative memo detailing reduction, August 9; Empire Plan contribution rates for participating agencies, August 9; results of Brookhaven Hospital election, showing win by NYSUT, August 8; Department of Civil Service Empire Plan quarterly experience report, August 5; materials re new PERB grievance resolution plan combining mediation and arbitration; analysis by NYSUT legal counsel re U.S. Supreme Court decision in CWA v Beck re agency fees, with text of brief, July 1
- Training Correspondence, 1989 (Box 28, Folder 13)
  Survey with list of 27 possible training topics, request for selection of top 7, May 1; handwritten notes on education reform
- Albany Regional Office: Correspondence, 1986 (Box 29, Folder 1)
  Proposal for EIT fund distribution, November 19; memo re need for legislative change in Taylor Law re per diem substitute employees, December 1; PERB administrative law judge decision in Wayne-Finger Lakes BOCES and Wayne-Finder Lakes BOCES Teachers' Association, with cover memo recommending case for use in workshop, October 29; memo re case at Ravena Coeymans Selkirk Teachers Association in which a teacher refused to join the union based on religious objection and requested a review of the agency fee policy, with clipping from Adventist Review and text of Equal Employment Opportunity Act of 1972, September 30; memo re staff training for investigatory interviews, September 23; new required form, Written Verified Claim, replacing Notice of Claim, and cover memos between Jim Conti and NYSUT legal counsel, July; North Colonie Teachers Association newsletter, NCTA Newsline, praising NYSUT staff, with cover memo to Jim Conti and others, June 10; memo requesting staff assistance to organize a regional substitutes' union for the southern Adirondack region, May 19; request for NYSUT staff support at rally for Waterford-Halfmoon contract settlement, April 16; memo to Jim Conti re substitute teacher organizing campaign for Washington, Warren, and Northern Saratoga counties, April 14; request for attorney to participate on panel discussion re 3020a cases for Guilderland Supervisors Unit, March 3; draft letter re voluntary services, proposed in response to controversy at Guilderland district in which work-to-rule action led to charges of illegal strike, with response from Jim Conti, advising against it, February
- Albany Regional Office: Leon Lieberman Coordinator's Reports, 1986 (Box 29, Folder 2)
  Monthly regional staff director's and coordinator's reports
- Dutchess County Community College Meeting, 1986 (Box 29, Folder 3)